<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Matt Miller</title>
    <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Matt Miller</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://thisismattmiller.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Glitch</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/glitch/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/glitch/</guid>
      <description>Glitch Migration and Maintenance Jul 23 2025 Intro This month Glitch.com shut down, ending hosting for the projects there. They gave folks about a month to migrate their projects off the site. This also included paying customers, like me, who had the pro plan which cost $99 a year. A month is not a very long time at all, especially for paying customers, but that’s just like my opinion. The bottom line is they cut the power, so all of my projects there are gone, so after being salty about it I spent time this weekend doing the worst, most boring thing, maintenance on my personal hobby projects… Flowers for Glitch The way it ended is very lame, but I forgive them since it was really cool while it lasted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hathi PD 2025</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/hathi-pd-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/hathi-pd-2025/</guid>
      <description>HathiTrust 1929 Pubic Domain Data and tools to explore 50,000 1929/2025 public domain titles in HathiTrust Feb 5 2025 Intro Towards the end of the year HathiTrust quietly posts a collection of their resources that are set to enter the public domain in the new year. This is such a great resource and for the past few years I’ve done some visualistions or lists for 1925, 1926, 1927 and 1928.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WoodBlockShop</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/woodblockshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/woodblockshop/</guid>
      <description>WoodBlockShop Using Segment Anything, LLaVA and other methods on a 14K image corpus Dec 16 2024 I came across people sharing the Plantin-Moretus Museum collection site and I really liked it. The 14,000 woodcuts are obviously all very different but the monochromatic cohesion of the collection ties it together. I thought it would be a great collection to try some of the various image based machine learning techniques I’ve seen recently.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Banned Metadata</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/banned-metadata/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/banned-metadata/</guid>
      <description>Banned Metadata Analysis of PEN America 2022-2023 Banned and Challenged Book Metadata Sep 27 2024 Intro I&#39;m writing this at the end of Banned Book week 2024, which in recent years has become much more poignant as there are literally books being banned in the US. PEN America released info that for 2023-2024 there is over 10,000 instances of books being challenged or banned. They haven’t released the data or details for this year, but they did create a spreadsheet of books that were challenged or banned last year, July 2022 - June 2023:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lomax Whisper</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/lomax-whisper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/lomax-whisper/</guid>
      <description>Lomax &amp;amp; Whisper.cpp Automatic transcription of Alan Lomax’s 1938 Midwest Folk Song Collection using Whisper.cpp Sep 12 2024 Sound to Data Whisper(.cpp) Alan Lomax Collection of Michigan and Wisconsin Recordings The Shape of Sound Many Models - Least Bad? Web Component Player LLM Enrichment Search Interface Mutable Metadata Now I&#39;m going to sing a song like you&#39;re dying Code Links Sound to Data This post reviews a small project applying the Whisper speech-to-text model on an early 20th century folk song collection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LCNAF Anagrams</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/lcnaf-anagrams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/lcnaf-anagrams/</guid>
      <description>LCNAF Anagrams Apr 1 2024 LCNAF (Library of Congress Authority File) has over eleven million names of things ranging from people to geographic locations. I look at this data all the time, and it must have rotted my brain because I started thinking how there were probably a lot of names that if rearranged would spell other names in the file. Turns out there are—in just the personal and corporate categories alone there are over 4000 sets of 5 or more names that all use the same letters to spell themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating Your Docker Wikibase</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/migrating-your-docker-wikibase/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/migrating-your-docker-wikibase/</guid>
      <description>Migrating Your Docker Wikibase Mar 20 2024 At Semantic Lab @ Pratt we were early-ish adopters of the Wikibase Docker distrubtuion (now deprecated and archived, replaced with the wikibase-release-pipeline). It was nice to have a system that was ready to deploy with minimal configuration, we used version 1.31 for many years and it worked fairly well. Like all system maintenance eventually you need to upgrade servers and I needed to now move our Wikibase to a new server and upgrade to use version 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using GPT on Library Collections</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/using-gpt-on-library-collections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/using-gpt-on-library-collections/</guid>
      <description>Using GPT on Library Collections Use cases for applying GPT3/3.5/4 on a full text collection March 30 2023 Intro Ground Rules Domain - Susan B Anthony Daybooks Correspondences Writings Comparing GPT3 / 3.5 / 4 Provenance Don’t call it Boutique Scale vs Voltage Should you use GPT? Conclusion Intro Here in early 2023 the breathless hype surrounding ChatGPT/GPT4 is honestly reaching annoying levels. On twitter every would be tech influencer Nostradamus is posting a screenshot of some tiny conversation they had with a computer and predicting the death of an entire industry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jan 6th Overflow</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/jan-6th-overflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/jan-6th-overflow/</guid>
      <description>Jan 6th Overflow 2022 Watching the live stream of Trump&#39;s speech on Jan 6th 2021 on YouTube I was struck by the comment section on the video. Rendered pretty much useless by the sheer volume of comments flying up the window. It consisted of mostly Trump supporters shouting into the internet. Watching it trying to gauge some kind of zeitgeist of what was about to happen. At the time I lived only a few blocks from the National Mall and the situation was giving me serious anxiety.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animated Gifs in US Elections</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/animated-gifs-in-us-elections/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/animated-gifs-in-us-elections/</guid>
      <description>Animated Gifs in US Elections Mining the Library of Congress web archives for political Gifs Dec 1 2021 Intro Problem Space Official Gifs User Content Gifs Getting Weird With User Content Gifs Technical - How to get started working with this dataset Intro A new dataset was announced by the prolific data releasing web archiving team and LC Labs at the Library of Congress. I really enjoy working with the datasets they put out because: 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leeks: ParkMobile</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/leeks-parkmobile/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/leeks-parkmobile/</guid>
      <description>Leeks: ParkMobile What&#39;s in a (car) name? June 9 2021 About the Leeks Series: This blog series uses publicly found dataset leaks, breaches and scrapes to do something interesting or fun. Personal identifying information will never be posted. Nor will any data be redistributed and you will never find any information on how to obtain the dataset. I will however use the data in aggregate for visualizations or reporting on trends found in the dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repeated Hunt</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/repeated-hunt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/repeated-hunt/</guid>
      <description>Repeated Hunt 2020, 7 minutes These layered 18th century hand colored engravings come from the collection of Caroline King Duer who gave them to the Cooper Hewitt. Duer was an author as well as an editor in the 1930s at Vogue, heading up the house furnishing section of the magazine. Hunting scenes are a common theme in 18th century and earlier engravings. A desirable aristocratic activity whose depiction begins appearing in paintings, etchings and eventually housewares and even stylized in wall paper designs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISBN Uh-Oh</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/isbn-uh-oh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/isbn-uh-oh/</guid>
      <description>Example Tweet	Example Tweet ISBN Uh-Oh Dec 2020, Twitter Bot ISBNs are numbers given books by publishers to help uniquely identify them. Every time a new book comes out or a new edition of a book (translation, 2nd edition, paperback, etc) it gets a new ISBN. These numbers are very useful for libraries, book sellers, book readers to help locate books and organize them. Sometimes it turns out that two books get the same number, this problem can turn up in large collaborative cataloging systems like Worldcat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ostraca</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/ostraca/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/ostraca/</guid>
      <description>Ostraca 2020, 2 hours 34 minutes In the weeks after the 2020 presidential election you could stream live video of the Philadelphia vote counting process. You could watch as dozens of workers claid in safety vests sorted and counted ballots. This low paid or volunteer work is the invisible labor that makes the machinery of US elections work. Ostraca reuses that footage but erases everything except the fluorescent safety vests worn by the workers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Renewed</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/non-renewed/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/non-renewed/</guid>
      <description>Non-Renewed Copyright Analysis Digging into NYPL&#39;s digitized CCE Corpus Jul 22 2020 Intro Due to the bizarre nature of US copyright many works published in the mid-20th century are actually in the public domain. If a resource was published in a specific range of years and did not have its copyright renewed that material is likely open. The problem is determining this status because the records of this renewed status is locked up in the Library of Congress Copyright Office’s Catalog of Copyright Entries (CCE).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eclipsed Time</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/eclipsed-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/eclipsed-time/</guid>
      <description>Maya Lin&#39;s Eclipsed Time Time telling in a pandemic Apr 12 2020 “Time is broken” seems to be the thing everyone can agree with lately. The last few weeks folks I’ve talked to always seem to casually mention how they don’t know what day of the week it is. Co-workers, family, friends, students, it’s different for everyone, days feel too long, or seem too short, or a mixture of both.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Library of Congress Web Archives</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/library-of-congress-web-archives/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/library-of-congress-web-archives/</guid>
      <description>Library of Congress Web Archives Big Picture Apr 23 2020 It was great to see the web archiving team at the Library of Congress recently celebrate twenty years of archiving. And they had a great article in the New York Times last month. I really like the LC web archive for a number of reasons. One is that it is heavily curated, meaning a lot of metadata is created for each site that is archived.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smithsonian Open Access Data Release</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/smithsonian-open-access-data-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/smithsonian-open-access-data-release/</guid>
      <description>Smithsonian Open Access Data Release A First Look Feb 28 2020 The Smithsonian Open Access release has put a trove of cultural heritage digital assets and data in the public commons. I wanted to show how you could start exploring and using the data. If you are comfortable running some Python scripts this post will quickly give you a head start. If not you might still be interested in following along as we look at some discoveries and visualizations I’ve created along the way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Repotting Old Digital Humanities Projects</title>
      <link>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/repotting-old-digital-humanities-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thisismattmiller.com/post/repotting-old-digital-humanities-projects/</guid>
      <description>Repotting Old Digital Humanities Projects Two Test Cases Jan 31 2020 Knowing how to stop doing things is an important skill to learn. Kind of like learning to say no to things when you don’t have the capacity to do them. I&#39;ve seen requirements around sustainability and sunsetting, that is how to wind down or retire a project become more prevalent on grant applications and funding processes. I&#39;ve also seen sunsetting become more of a topic around digital humanities and cultural heritage projects.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
